<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Snapshots of a Life</title><link>http://michaelkarpeles.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://michaelkarpeles.com/feeds/mek-michael-e-karpeles.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><item><title>Learning Chinese</title><link>http://michaelkarpeles.com/learning-chinese.html</link><description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning Chinese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning, in general&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning involves two stages. Learning how to learn, and then actually
learning. That is to say, a substantial portion of the learning
process for a new domain involves determining which practices,
resources, and methods are most effective. Building an effective
learning model or framework requires one first has choosen criteria
for measuring or evaluating progress, which is typically satisfied by
a set of goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Choosing Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goals is to be able to have:
1. text conversations 
2. translate and read a chinese classic piece of literature
3. participate in basic conversation
4. read signs in san francisco
5. travel to china without dying, or worse, offending anyone&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Successful Frameworks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases where we have prior experience, we can apply
methodologies we've identified as successful to similar domains. Many
techniques for learning French can be obtained, for instance, from
having first learned another romance language. For a topic which
is significantly foreign to us, we must rely on others' knowledge
(e.g. take a course, read a book, hire a tutor) or evolve our own
strategies and frameworks to structure our learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this is an exercise which you find challenging, consider reading a
book like Polya's, "How to Solve It" [3] or "How to Learn Anything
Quickly" [4]. It may seem silly, but learning strategies for
approaching learning (while quite meta in principle) is much the same
as "teaching a [wo]man to fish".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Words of warning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal experience is, great resources can come from anywhere, but
they are often incomplete (in terms of gaps in content or
unsatisfactory features) and need to be supplimented with other
sources. An example is relying on one website for learning stroke
order and another for pronounciation. There is a lot of risk in
relying on too many fragmented sources as they will likely have
disagreements about what content should be introduced and
when. Additionally, context switching (changing from concentrating on
one source to another) is distracting -- it takes time to adjust to
different teaching styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building your framework or strategies on top a central foundation,
like a lesson book or a native speaking tutor is likely the most
effective (not necessarily the cheapest) way to bootstrap learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My Learning Philosophy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal preference is, I prefer not spending money on
resources. I'd much rather repay the community with learnings of my
own. That said, I appreciate some resources require significant
investment and care in order to exist and if I have to pay for
anything, I'd rather it be knowledge. Wikipedia and the Internet
Archive, for instance, have necessary server and electricity costs in
order to be able to provide their services to the public -- I take
pride in supporting these costly initiatives which aim to make
knowledge more open and accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, as I believe knowledge should be accessible to everyone, I
am going to try to highlight resources which can be legally obtained,
free of charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Chinese&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Largest population. More than 5 times more people speak Mandarin
Chinese than speak English. [1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applicability / Competitive Advantage. There is a large spanish
speaking community in california. Spanish is a more widely spoken
language than English, world wide. I took spanish for five
years. Other than ordering food in Spanish restaurants, reading the
occasional spanish news paper, and travelling to Mexico and Costa
Rica, I haven't had many practical opportunities for applying the
language. Perhaps this is due to cultural differences or a side effect
of not having many spanish friends I can speak with on a regular
basis. My personal experience is, I found a lot more Chinese speaking
people in my computer science classes than Spanish speaking and
honestly, being able to communicate with academics and researchers who
share my interests is very important to me. Finally, a great deal of
the world's manufactoring occurs in China. If you can't ask questions
as a native, it's easy to be taken advantage of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friends. The top reason why I am learning chinese is, I have a lot of
smart friends who I respect who decided to learn Chinese. I don't want
to be left out of conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's different. German, french, spanish, and itallian are all
relatively similar. They use roman characters, have comparable
grammars, and even cognates. If you know a few words in a sentence,
there's a chance you can guess the other words. Moreover, you can at
least sound them out and read these languages, even if you have no
idea what you're reading. Chinese, on the other hand, is like learning
two languages: the written language and the spoken language. I am
unaware of any way (patterns, strategies) of infering written
characters from spoken Chinese or vice versa. By the way, did you know
vice versa means "a change", "an alternate order" (vice) "turn about"
(versa) -- thus the "order turned about"? I find etymology, as in this
example, to be a great way to remember words, discover similar roots,
and achieve greater understanding of a language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cultural Insight, Literature. The language has unique idioms and
insights. There The Four Books &amp;amp; Five Classics [2], The Art of War&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0775272.html
[2] https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Books
[3] http://books.google.com/books/about/How_to_Solve_It.html?id=z_hsbu9kyQQC
[4] http://www.amazon.com/Learn-Anything-Quickly-Ricki-Linksman/dp/0760728364&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;If not Chinese&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I contemplated learning japanese, but there just aren't enough
speakers outside of japan. I occassionally read manga or watch anime
so I thought these activities could be a good way to keep myself
engaged and accountable to practicing a language. I also have
contemplated learning hebrew, croation, or russian, because I have
family in these places and the languages offer similar challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can sound out basic german, french, and spanish phonetically. Given
chinese characters (hanzi) I am complete illiterate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Experiments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to pick one piece of classic Chinese literature and start learning / copying its characters and translating it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Resources (in order of discovery)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dialogues&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL0A5BF42C1FBB672B
http://cctv.cntv.cn/lm/learningchinese/program/index.shtml&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Phrases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Chinese_(Mandarin)/Lesson_2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Character Lookup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.nciku.com/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dictionaries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.mdbg.net/chindict
http://www.nciku.com/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Explained Texts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://ctext.org/dictionary.pl?if=en&amp;amp;id=20910&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pronounciations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://dictionary.hantrainerpro.com/
http://www.standardmandarin.com/
http://www.nciku.com/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stroke Order&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.chinesehideout.com/tools/strokeorder/index.php?c=%E4%BD%A0%E5%A5%BD&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning Chinese so far has been a frustrating process, mostly because
learning a language, itself, is an art. What is the best way to
practice? What are the best resources? What are common mistakes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided it could be helpful for me to document my progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Choose a Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goals is to be able to have
1. text conversation
2. read ____
3. speak basic conversation
4. read signs in san francisco
5. travel to china and not die&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;graspchinese.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep an electronic document with words as &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lined paper&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flashcards&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use paper flash cards as one of the most important elements to
memorizing chinese characters (or hanzi) is drawing them using the
correct stroke orders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Literal meaning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't settle for colloquial translations, try to understand literal
meaning. For instance, it is often taught that 你好 (Ni3 Hao3) means
hello. It really means "you" (ni3) "good" (hao3). Once you commit to
breaking phrases down to, and understanding, the language's simplest
components, you begin to notice trends which make future learning much
faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to read&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Books_and_Five_Classics&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Mek (Michael E. Karpeles)</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:michaelkarpeles.com,2014-08-26:learning-chinese.html</guid><category>learning</category><category>chinese</category></item></channel></rss>